A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Homes, Series I FA318
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Homes, Series I
1885-1961
Rockefeller Archive Center
Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial
Mauze, Abby Rockefeller
Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison)
Spelman Fund
Rockefeller, John D.
Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease
China Medical Board (U.S)
Rockefeller family
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.)
Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich
International Education Board
General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.)
Spelman family
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine)
Standard Oil Company
Rockefeller Brothers Fund
Rockefeller Foundation
Rockefeller, David
Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.)
Davison Fund
Sealantic Fund, New York
Rockefeller, Winthrop
Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth)
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA318
98 Cubic Feet 169 document cases, and additional materials.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research except where particular restrictions are noted.
Material in the Rockefeller family collections which provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net worth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from scholarly access.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Arrangement note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records are arranged by subject matter in 27 series. Most of these series are wholly or partially open for research. The series are:
A John D. Rockefeller, Sr.; C Business Interests; D Civic Interests; E Cultural Interests; F Economic Reform Interests; G Educational Interests; H Friends and Services; I Homes; J Housing Interests; K Medical Interests; L Real Estate; M Maps and Memorabilia; N Religious Interests; O Rockefeller Boards; P Welfare - General Files; Q World Affairs; R Welfare - Youth Files; S Documents; T Public Relations; U Public Land Law Review Commission; V Greenrock; W Properties; X Costume Collection; Y Media; Z John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal; AA Abby Aldrich Rockefeller; AC Abby Rockefeller Mauzé
Biographical/Historical note
The central figure in the creation and operation of the Standard Oil Company during its rise to the top of the petroleum industry, John D. Rockefeller (JDR) established for the family a leading role in business and philanthropy. From the days of his earliest employment, Rockefeller, a devout Baptist, was generous in his giving to worthy causes, especially those of a religious nature. During the 1890s he developed an orderly system of philanthropic giving through an office staff that included his close advisor, Frederick T. Gates (1853-1929) and his son, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960). With the advise of these and other associates, Rockefeller established the University of Chicago, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), the Rockefeller Foundation, and other philanthropic organizations working nationally and internationally in the fields of education, religion, and health. Rockefeller's total donations to philanthropic endeavors are estimated to have been $540 million.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.) joined his father's office on October 1, 1897. He oversaw the expansion and diversification of the philanthropic work begun by his father. During his lifetime, the younger Rockefeller gave more than $537 million to educational, religious, cultural, medical, and other charitable projects.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and his wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (1874-1948), passed the Rockefeller philanthropic impulse on to their children. John D. 3rd (1906-1978), Nelson A. (1908-1979), Laurance S. (1910-2004), Winthrop (1912-1973), and David (1915-) further expanded and diversified Rockefeller influence and interests, establishing their own philanthropic organizations, most notably the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1940), and becoming more active politically.
Scope and Contents note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller (OMR) materials document the increasing role assumed by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in the management of Rockefeller affairs and amply document his business and philanthropic affairs. They also chronicle the entrance of JDR Jr.'s sons, John D. 3rd, Nelson A., Laurance S., Winthrop, and David, into the world of business, philanthropy, civic leadership, and politics as they joined the office.
This material contains correspondence, reports, pamphlets, memoranda, deeds, maps, contracts, reports, minutes, charters, certificates of incorporation, clippings, diaries, notebooks, calendars, and memorabilia.
There is a microfilm card index of personal and institutional names.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 02
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Arrangement note
This series is arranged in thirteen sections, as follows:
Transfer of Property, Florida Property, Lakewood Property, 740 Park Avenue Apartment, Richford Property, Pocantico Hills, Seal Harbor, 10 West 54th Street, 4 West 54th Street, 12 West 54th Street, One Beekman Place, Hills Realty Company, Inc., House Books. Some oversized material has been separated and placed at the end of the collection.
Scope and Contents note
The Homes series documents the management of four of John D. Rockefeller, Sr.'s and John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s estates and their New York City homes. The estates are Ormond Beach, Florida; Lakewood, New Jersey; Pocantico Hills, New York; and Seal Harbor, Maine. The New York City homes are 4, 10, and 12 West 54th Street and the apartment at 740 Park Avenue. There is also information regarding John D. Rockefeller 3rd's apartment at One Beekman Place. Most of the material deals with property purchases, employees, the construction of homes, out buildings, and private roads, relations with neighbors and local communities, the contents of the houses (particularly art collections), and the general maintenance and operation of the various homes. The correspondence is between members of the family and the family office on the one hand, and estate managers, employees, contractors, real estate agents, neighbors, members of the various communities, and art dealers on the other.
The Homes series is divided into twelve sections, nine concern the homes listed above, and three others concern Richford; Transfer of Property; and House Books. The Richford section contains information on the purchase of the site of John D. Rockefeller, Sr.'s birthplace and surrounding property in the 1920s to prevent its commercial exploitation. The Transfer of Property section concerns the transfer of ownership of the various estates from John D. Rockefeller, Sr. to his son John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and the distribution of John D. Rockefeller, Sr.'s personal effects after his death. The House Books are listings and descriptions of the contents of the various houses. These lists also include the contents of Bassett Hall at Williamsburg, Virginia, and John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s office at Room 5600. Also included in these books are distributions of the personal effects of John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, and Martha Baird Rockefeller after their respective deaths.
Aside from offering an insight into the management of the family estates and homes, this series also illustrates John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s personal interests in the conservation of land and wildlife and in collecting Chinese porcelains and other art objects. The series also gives many examples of the attention he gave to the details in every affair he handled.
The collection measures 98 cubic feet. The material covers the years 1885-1961, and the family members who figure prominently in the papers are John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and John D. Rockefeller 3rd. John D. Rockefeller, Sr., Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Winthrop Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, and David Rockefeller also appear. Of the Rockefeller family advisors who appear, Robert W. Gumbel and Charles O. Heydt are the most prominent.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records include: FA310 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
FA312 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Business Interests
FA313 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests
FA314 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests
FA315 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Economic Reform Interests
FA316 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Educational Interests
FA317 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Friends and Services
FA319 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Housing Interests
FA320 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Medical Interests
FA321 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Real Estate
FA322 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Maps and Memorabilia
FA323 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests
FA324 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards
FA325 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - General Files
FA326 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs
FA327 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - Youth Files
FA329 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations
FA333 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Costume Collection
FA334 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Media
FA335 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal
FA336 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller
FA337 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Rockefeller Mauze
Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); World War I; World War II; Travel; United States; Urban policy; Urban renewal; Religious institutions; Restoration and conservation; Rockefeller family -- Art collections; State governments -- United States; Housing rehabilitation; Public relations; Public welfare; Religion; Health insurance; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Government policy; Folk art; Federal government -- United States; Family planning; Education -- United States; Education; Economics; Economic policy; Economic development; Art; Art, Modern; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Arts; Business; Capital investments; Business enterprises, Foreign; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Charitable contributions; Charities -- Investments; Charities; Civic improvement; Child welfare; International economic relations; International cooperation; International relations; International education; Juvenile delinquency; International relations -- United States; Medical care; Maternal health services; Public policy; Public health administration; Public health; Prohibition; Political science; Political campaigns -- United States; Performing arts; Parks -- New York (State); New York (State); New York (N.Y.); Medical sciences; Medical research; Medical education; Philanthropy; Philanthropy -- United States; Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial; Mauze, Abby Rockefeller; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); Spelman Fund; Rockefeller, John D.; Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease; China Medical Board (U.S); Rockefeller family; Rockefeller Center; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich); Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); International Education Board; General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.); Spelman family; Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman; Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine); Standard Oil Company; Rockefeller Brothers Fund; Rockefeller Foundation; Rockefeller, David; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Davison Fund; Sealantic Fund, New York; Rockefeller, Winthrop; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth); Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
- Transfer of Property
  - Transfer of Property - 4 West 54th Street, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Distribution of pictures and books by John D. Rockefeller to friends and relatives from 4 West 54th Street. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    File Plan note
    270
  - Transfer of Property - 4 West 54th Street - Correspondence, 1924-1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Legal correspondence on sale by John D. Rockefeller to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. of all his property. Values placed on property.
  - Transfer of Property - 4 West 54th Street - China, 1918-1925 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Distribution of china to Alta Rockefeller Prentice and John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Transfer of Property - 4 West 54th Street - Insurance on Appraisal Valuations, 1914-1924 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Value of paintings and portraits.
  - Transfer of Property - Bills of Sale and Leases Between John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1909, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Bill of Sale, Ohio, September 29, 1909. Lakewood, Mount Pleasant, Greenburgh, West 55th Street garage, Ormond, July 7, 1925. Bill of Sale, Lakewood and Ormond-Lease.
  - Transfer of Property - 4 West 54th Street - Furnishings, 1918-January 1925 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Lists of items sent to Alta Rockefeller Prentice and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in 1918. Lists of items distributed by John D. Rockefeller through John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to several members of his family, 1925. Includes china, silver, pictures, art work. Some gifts outside family. A few items sold. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Transfer of Property - 4 West 54th Street - Furnishings, February-December 1925 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Transfer of Property - John D. Rockefeller to John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1922-1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Preparation for transfer. Correspondents include Thomas M. Debevoise.
  - Transfer of Property - John D. Rockefeller to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. - Sale at American Art Galleries, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Sale of paintings owned by John D. Rockefeller and of John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s porcelains.
- Florida Property
  - Florida Property - General
    Florida payrolls, house repairs, code messages. Transfer of property to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Local gifts by John D. Rockefeller. Closing of home after John D. Rockefeller's death. Shipment of personal effects from Florida. Relations between superintendent and housekeeper. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles O. Heydt, F. W. Perrin, F. A. Evans.
    185
    - Florida Property - General, 1918-1922 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Florida Property - General, 1923-1934 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Florida Property - General, 1935-1939 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Conditions Governing Access note
      Open for scholarly research with prior archival review.
    - Florida Property - General, 1940-1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Florida Property - General - Sale of White House, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    To professor for $25,000.
  - Florida Property - General - Sale to C. L. Garner, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Sale of White House not completed.
  - Florida Property - General - George N. Rigby, 1920-1936 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Mayor of Ormond Beach, received gifts from John D. Rockefeller.
  - Florida Property - General - Causeway Construction, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Rockefeller contribution to bridge repair costs.
  - Florida Property - General - Jennie G. Harris, 1935-1940 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Florida Property - General - Fred W. Perrin, 1934-1947 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Florida Property - General - Taxes, 1935-1940 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    City, County, and School taxes. Summaries.
  - Florida Property - General - Termination Gifts, 1940-1942 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Severance pay to estate employees when property sold.
  - Florida Property - Purchase of Property, 1918-1919 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Delivery of deeds, abstract of title. Disagreements over furniture included in sale. John D. Rockefeller purchased two houses at Ormond. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, W. S. Mitchell, Harwood Huntington.
  - Florida Property - 1924 Purchase and Sale of Land - George N. Rigby, 1924-1929 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Rigby traded wth John D. Rockefeller on two parcels of land in Ormond Beach. Rigby sold his, his purchaser defaulted on a mortgage running to John D. Rockefeller. Mortgage foreclosed. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, George N. Rigby, E. V. Cary.
  - Florida Property - 1924 Purchase and Sale of Land - George N. Rigby, 1930-1954 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Florida Property - Tax Lien - Purchase of Lots 16, 25, 18, 1930-1933 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Purchase of tax liens to obtain lots adjoining Casement property. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Thomas M. Debevoise.
  - Florida Property - Tax Lien - Purchase of Lots 16, 25, 18, 1934-1937 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Florida Property - Appraisal, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    1925 appraisal of Casements and surrounding property owned by John D. Rockefeller. Correspondents include George N. Rigby.
    295
  - Florida Property - Sale, 1937-1940 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Search for a buyer. Suggestions on use of estate. Correspondents include Charles O. Heydt, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., F. W. Perrin, Winthrop Rockefeller.
    185.1
  - Florida Property - Sale - Sketches, Photostats and Blue Prints, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Florida Property - Sale - Previews, Inc., 1940 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Book of photographs of Casement. Engaged to promote sale, prepare brochure. Correspondents include Charles O. Heydt.
    185.1A
    General note
    Photographs removed to Photograph Collection.
  - Florida Property - Sale - Graham Eckes School, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Efforts of school to buy property. Deal fell through when school could not borrow necessary funds. Corresondents include Charles O. Heydt, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Inez Graham.
    185.2
  - Florida Property - 1940 Sale - P. L. Willis and Miss Van Woy, 1940-1943 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Terms of sale to P. L. Willis. Negotiations through Charles O. Heydt. Assignment of property to Miss Van Woy for use as Junior College. Correspondents include P. L. Willis, Maud Van Woy, Charles O. Heydt, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    185.3
  - Florida Property - 1940 Sale - P. L. Willis and Miss Van Woy - Contract and Payments (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Florida Property - 1940 Sale - P. L. Willis and Miss Van Woy - Newspaper Clippings, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    On sale.
  - Florida Property - Willis-Van Woy Suit, 1943, 1942-1945 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Issue over price paid by Miss Van Woy to Willis for property on assignment. Charles O. Heydt called as witness for establishing facts of transaction. Rockefeller not involved in suit. Correspondents include Charles O. Heydt, P. L. Willis, Maud Van Woy.
    185.31
- Lakewood, NJ, Property
  - Lakewood Property - General
    Purchase of property. Sale of property. Pay of help. Management problems. 1918 inventory of Golf House. Local gifts. Distribution of milk. Distribution of things from Golf House after John D. Rockefeller's death. Payment of general expenses. Fred Buswell, superintendent of estate, his family. Freeholders of Ocean County consider demolishing Golf House. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Fred L. Buswell.
    153
    - Lakewood Property - General, 1901-1911 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Lakewood Property - General, 1912-1931 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Lakewood Property - General, 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Lakewood Property - General, 1934-1937 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Lakewood Property - General, 1934-1937 (Box 4, Folder 39A)
      Restricted - Personnel material.
    - Lakewood Property - General, 1938-1940 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Lakewood Property - General, 1938-1940 (Box 4, Folder 40A)
      Restricted - Personnel material
    - Lakewood Property - General, 1941-1961 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Lakewood Property - General, 1941-1961 (Box 4, Folder 41A)
  - Lakewood Property - General - Taxes, 1936-1939 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Lakewood Property - Purchase of Property - Fay Property, 1906-1913 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Lakewood Property - Purchase of Property - Fisher Property, 1914-1918 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Lakewood Property - Purchase of Property - Golf House, 1902-1913 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Lakewood Property - Purchase of Property - Irons and Pulsifer, 1902-1907 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Lakewood Property - Purchase of Property - Johnson Property, 1911-1914 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Lakewood Property - Purchase of Property - Johnson Property, 1915 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Lakewood Property - Purchase of Property - Kearny, 1903-1906 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Lakewood Property - Purchase of Property - Matthews Property, 1925-1927 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Lakewood Property - Purchase of Property - Starr Cottage, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Lakewood Property - Purchase of Property - Statements and Purchases, 1901-1904 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Lakewood Property - Purchase of Property - Turner Property, 1913-1914 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Lakewood Property - Purchase of Property - Miscellaneous, 1904-1919 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Lakewood Property - 5th Street Lots, 1920-1943 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    Giving property to Mrs. de Cuevas. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Alta Rockefeller Prentice.
  - Lakewood Property - Gift to Ocean County, 1939-1940 (Box 6, Folder 56)
    Transfer of property to County of Ocean. Appraisal of property. Comments on use of estate by Giants. Correspondents include Jay Downer.
    153.2
  - Lakewood Property - Gift to Ocean County, 1941-1954 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Lakewood Property - Gift to Ocean County - Correspondence with H. E. Newman and County Board of Freeholders, 1939-1961 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    County Board of Freeholders. Clarification of gift.
  - Lakewood Property - Gift to Ocean County - Agreement, June 27, 1940, 1940-1941 (Box 6, Folder 59)
    Agreement and deeds.
  - Lakewood Property - Gift to Ocean County - Clippings, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Lakewood Property - Sales, 1937, 1925-1942 (Box 6, Folder 61)
    Disposition of Lakewood properties. Many offers from brokers and charities. Correspondents include Charles O. Heydt.
    153.1
  - Lakewood Property - Sales, 1937 - Lists of Rooms and Charles O. Heydt Memo, 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Lakewood Property - Lakewood Survey and Sale, 1925, 1925-1940 (Box 6, Folder 63)
    290
- 740 Park Avenue, NYC, Apartment
  - 740 Park Avenue Apartment - General
    Preparations for moving into apartment, utilities, elevator, alterations. Caretaker, G. Samalens. Neighbor Mr. L.K. Thorne. Approximate date of occupancy. Apartment problems. Purchase of Foy apartment on 17th Floor. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Mrs. George Brewster, Clarence J. Shearn, Douglas Gibbons.
    245
    - 740 Park Avenue Apartment - General, 1936-1937 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - 740 Park Avenue Apartment - General, 1938-1939 (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - 740 Park Avenue Apartment - General, 1940-1953 (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - 740 Park Avenue Apartment - General, 1954-1959 (Box 7, Folder 67)